Before we start, I gave
the same talk at Stanford
quite recently.
I suggested to the
people inviting me
I could just give one talk
and both audiences could come,
but they would prefer it
as two separate talks.
So if you went to
this talk recently,
I suggest you leave now.
You won't learn anything new.
OK.
What I'm going to do is
combine some recent ideas
in neural networks
to try to explain
how a neural network
could represent
part-whole hierarchies
without violating
any of the basic principles
of how neurons work.
And I'm going to explain
these ideas in terms
of an imaginary system.
I started writing a design
document for a system.
And in the end, I decided
the design document by itself
was quite interesting.
So this is just vaporware,
stuff that doesn't exist.
Little bits of it now exist.
But somehow I find
it easy to explain
the ideas in the context
of an imaginary system.
So most people now
studying neural networks
are doing engineering,
and they don't really
care if it's exactly
how the brain works.
They're not trying to
understand how the brain works.
They're trying to
make cool technology.
And so a hundred layers
is fine in a ResNet.
Weight sharing is fine in
a convolutional neural net.
Some researchers, particularly
computational neuroscientists,
investigate artificial
neural networks
in an attempt to understand how
the brain might actually work.
I think we still got a lot
to learn from the brain.
And I think it's
worth remembering
that for about half a
century, the only thing that
kept research on neural
networks going was the belief
that it must be possible
to make these things learn
complicated things
because the brain does.
So every image has a
different parse tree
that is the structure
of the wholes
in the parts in the image.
And in a real
neural network, you
can't dynamically allocate it.
You can't just grab
a bunch of neurons
and say, OK, you
now represent this
because you don't have
random access memory.
You can't just set the
weights of the neurons
to be whatever you like.
What a neuron does is
determined by its connections.
And they only change
slowly at least probably.
Mostly, they change slowly.
So the question is, if you can't
change what neurons do quickly,
how can you represent
a dynamic parse tree?
In symbolic AI,
it's not a problem.
You just grab a
piece of memory--
that's what it
normally amounts to--
and say this is
going to represent
a node in the
parse tree, and I'm
going to give it
pointers to other nodes,
other bits of memory that
represent other nodes.
So there's no problem.
For about five years, I played
with a theory called Capsules
where you say because you can't
allocate neurons on the fly,
you're going to allocate
them in advance.
So we can take
groups of neurons,
and we're going to allocate
them to different possible nodes
in a parse tree.
And most of these groups
of neurons for most images
are going to be silent.
A few are going to be active.
And then the ones that are
active we have to dynamically
hook them up into a parse tree.
So we have to have a way of
routing between these groups
of neurons.
So that was the Capsule theory.
And I had some very
competent people
working with me who
actually made it work,
but it was tough going.
My view is that some
ideas want to work,
and some ideas
don't want to work
and capsules are the
sort of in-between.
Things like backpropagation
just want to work.
You try them and they work.
There's other ideas I've had
that just don't want to work.
Capsules was sort of in
between, and we got it working.
But I now have a new
theory that could
be seen as a funny
kind of capsules model
in which each capsule is
universal, that is instead
of a capsule being dedicated
to a particular kind of thing,
each capsule can represent
any kind of thing,
but hardware still comes
in capsules, which are also
called embedding sometimes.
So the imaginary system I'll
talk about is called GLOM.
And in GLOM hardware gets
allocated to columns.
And each column
contains multiple levels
of representation
of what's happening
in a small patch of the image.
So within a column, you
might have a lower level
representation that
says it's a nostril.
And the next level up
might say it's a nose.
And the next level
up might say face,
the next level up a person.
And the top level
might say it's a party.
That's what the whole scene is.
And the idea for representing
part-whole hierarchies
is to use islands of agreement
between the embeddings
at these different levels.
So at the scene level,
at the top level,
you'd like the same embedding
for every patch of the image
because that patch is a patch
of the same scene everywhere.
But the object level
you'd like the embeddings
of all the different patches
that belong to the object
to be the same.
So as you go up this
hierarchy, you're
trying to make things
more and more the same.
And that's how you're
squeezing redundancy out.
The embedding vectors are the
things that act like pointers.
And the embedding
vectors are dynamic.
They're neural activations
rather than neural weights.
So it's fine to have
different embedding
vectors for every image.
So here's a little picture.
If you had a one
dimensional row of patches,
these are the columns
for the patches.
And you'd have something like
a convolutional neural net
as a front end.
And then after
the front end, you
produce your lowest
level embeddings
that say what's going on
in each particular patch.
And so that bottom
layer of black arrows
they're all different.
Of course, these
embeddings are thousands
of dimensions maybe hundreds
of thousands in your brain.
And so a two-dimensional
vector isn't right.
But at least I can
represent where
the two vectors are the same
by using the orientation.
So at the lowest
level, all the patches
will have different
representations,
but the next level up,
the first two patches,
they might be part of
a nostril, for example.
And so, yeah, they'll
have the same embedding.
But the next level up,
the first three patches
might be part of a nose.
And so they'll all have
the same embedding.
Notice that even though
what's in the image
is quite different,
at the part level,
those three red vectors are
all meant to be the same.
So what we're doing is we're
getting the same representation
for things that are
superficially very different.
We're finding spatial
coherence in an image
by giving the same
representation
to different things.
And at the object level, you
might have a nose and then
a mouth.
And they're the same face.
They're part of the same face.
And so all those
vectors are the same.
And this network
hasn't yet settled down
to produce on the unseen level.
So the islands of agreement are
what captured the parse tree.
Now they're a bit more
powerful than a parse tree.
They can capture things
like shut the heck up.
You can have shut and up can be
different vectors at one level.
But at a higher
level, shut and up can
have exactly the same vector,
namely the vector for shut up,
and they can be disconnected.
So you can do things a bit
more powerful than the context
free grammar here.
But basically it's a parse tree.
If you're a physicist, you can
think of each of these levels
as an Ising model with real
valued vectors rather than
binary spins.
Then you can think of them
being coordinate transforms
between levels, which makes
it much more complicated.
And then this is a kind
of multi-level Ising
model but with complicated
interactions between the levels
because, for example,
between the red arrows
and the black arrows
above them, you
need the coordinate transform
between a nose and a face.
But we'll come to that later.
If you're not a
physicist, ignore all
that because it won't help.
So I want to start on this--
I guess it's particularly
relevant for a natural language
course where you-- some of you
are not vision people by trying
to prove to you that coordinate
systems are not just something
invented by Descartes.
Coordinate systems were invented
by the brain a long time ago.
And we use coordinate
systems in understanding
what's going on in an image.
I also want to demonstrate
the psychological reality
of parse trees for an image.
So I'm going to do
this with a task
that I invented a long
time ago in the 1970s
when I was a grad
student in fact.
And you have to do this task to
get the full benefit from it.
So I want you to imagine on
the tabletop in front of you
there's a wire-frame cube.
And it's in the standard
orientation for a cube.
It's resting on the tabletop.
And from your point
of view, there's
a front bottom right hand
corner and a top back left hand
corner.
Here we go.
OK.
The front bottom
right hand corner
is resting on the tabletop along
with the four other corners.
And the top back
left hand corner
is at the other end of
a diagonal, which goes
through the center of the cube.
OK, so far so good.
Now, what we're going
to do is rotate the cube
so that this finger
stays on the tabletop
and the other finger is
vertically above it, like that.
This finger
shouldn't have moved.
OK.
So now we've got the
cube in an orientation
where that thing that was a
body diagonal is now vertical.
And all you've got to do
is take the bottom finger
because that's still
on the table top
and point with the bottom finger
to where the other corners
of the cube are.
So I want you to try do it.
Off you go.
Take your bottom finger.
Hold your top finger
at the other end
of that diagonal that's now been
made vertical and just point
to where the other corners are.
And luckily it zooms
so most of you--
other people won't be
able to see what you did.
And I can see that some
of you aren't pointing,
and that's very bad.
So most people point
out four of the corners.
And the most common response
is to say they're here, here,
here, and here.
They point out four corners in
a square halfway up that axis.
That's wrong as
you might imagine.
And it's easy to
see that it's wrong
because if you imagine the
cube in the normal orientation
and count the corners,
there's eight of them.
And these were two corners.
So where did the
other two corners go?
So one theory is that
when you rotated the cube,
the centripetal forces made them
fly off into your unconscious.
That's not a very good theory.
So what's happening
here is you have
no idea where the other corner,
are unless you're something
like a crystallographer.
You can sort of imagine
bits of the cube,
but you just can't imagine this
structure of the other corners,
what structure they form.
And this common
response that people
give of four corners in a square
is doing something very weird.
It's saying, well, OK.
I don't know where the
bits of the cube are,
but I know something
about cubes.
I know the corners
come in fours.
I know a cube has this four-fold
rotational symmetry or two
planes of bilateral symmetry
but right angles to one another.
And so what people do is
they preserve the symmetries
of the cube in their response.
They give four
corners in a square.
Now, what they've
actually pointed out
if they do that is two
pyramids each of which
has a square base.
One's upside down, and
they're stuck base to base.
So you can visualize
that quite easily.
So square base pyramid
with another one
stuck underneath it.
And so now you get
your two fingers
as the vertices of
those two pyramids.
And what's
interesting about that
is you've preserved the
symmetries of the cube
at the cost of doing something
pretty radical, which
is changing faces to vertices
and vertices to faces.
The thing you pointed out if
you did that was an octahedron.
It has eight faces
and 6 vertices.
A cube has six faces
and eight vertices.
So in order to
preserve the symmetries
you know about of
the cube, if you
did that, you've done
something really radical, which
has changed faces for vertices
and vertices for faces.
I should show you what
the answer looks like.
So I'm going to step back
and try and get enough light
and maybe you can see this cube.
So this is a cube.
And you can see
that the other edges
form a kind of zig-zag
ring around the middle.
So I got a picture of it.
So the colored rods
here are the other edges
of the cube, the ones that
don't touch your fingertips.
And your top fingers are
connected to the three vertices
of those flaps when
your bottom finger's
connected to the lowest
three vertices there.
And that's what a
cube looks like.
It's something you
had no idea about.
This is just a completely
different model of a cube.
It's so different.
I'll give it a different name.
I'll call it a hexahedron.
And the thing to
notice is a hexahedron
and a cube are
just conceptually,
utterly different.
You wouldn't even know one
was the same as the other
if you think about one as a
hexahedron and one as a cube.
It's like the ambiguity
between a tilted square
and an upright diamond
but more powerful
because you're not
familiar with it.
And that's my demonstration
that people really
do use coordinate systems.
And if you use a different
coordinate system
to describe things--
and here I forced you to use
a different coordinate system
by making the
diagonal be vertical
and asking you to describe it
relative to that vertical axis.
Then familiar things become
completely unfamiliar.
And when you do see them
relative to this new frame,
they just are a completely
different thing.
Notice that things like
convolutional neural nets
don't have that.
They can't look at
something and have
two utterly different
internal representations
of the very same thing.
I'm also showing you
that you do parsing.
So here I've colored
it so you parse it
into what I call the crown,
which is three triangular
flaps that slope
upwards and outwards.
Here's a different parsing,
the same green flaps
sloping upwards and outwards.
Now, we have a red flap
sloping downwards and outwards.
And we have a central rectangle.
And you just have the two
ends of the rectangle.
And if you perceive this, then
I close your eyes and ask you,
were there any
parallel edges there?
You're very well aware
that those two blue edges
were parallel.
Then you're typically not aware
of any other parallel edges
even though you know by
symmetry there must be pairs.
Similarly with the crown.
If you see the crown and then
I ask you to close your eyes
and ask you where
the parallel edge is,
you don't see any
parallel edges.
And that's because
the coordinate system
you're using for those flaps
don't line up with the edges.
Then you only notice
parallel edges
if they line up with the
coordinate system you see.
So here for the rectangle,
our parallel edges
align with the
coordinate system.
For the flaps, they don't.
So you're aware that those
two blue edges are parallel,
but you're not aware that one
of the green edges and one
of the red edges are parallel.
So this isn't like the
Necker cube ambiguity
where when it flips you
think that what's out there
in reality is different.
Things are at a different depth.
This is like, next weekend we
should be visiting relatives.
So if you take the
sentence "next weekend we
should be visiting
relatives," it can mean,
next weekend what we will be
doing is visiting relatives,
or it can mean, next
weekend what we will be
is visiting relatives.
Now those are completely
different senses.
They happen to have the
same truth conditions.
They mean the same thing in
the sense of truth conditions
because if you're visiting
relatives, what you are
is visiting relatives.
And it's that kind of ambiguity.
No disagreement about
what's going on in the world
but two completely different
ways of seeing the sentence.
This was drawn in the 1970s.
This is what AI was
like in the 1970s.
This is a sort of structural
description of the crown
interpretation.
So you have nodes for all
various parts in the hierarchy.
I've also put
something on the arcs.
That Rwx is the relationship
between the crown and the flap.
And that can be
represented by a matrix.
It's really the relationship
between the intrinsic frame
of reference of the crown
and the intrinsic frame
of reference of the flap.
Then notice that if I
change my viewpoint,
that doesn't change at all.
So that kind of relationship
would be a good thing
to put in the weights
of a neural network
because you like
the neural network
to be able to recognize shapes
independently of viewpoint.
And that Rwx is knowledge
about the shape that's
independent of viewpoint.
Here's the "zig-zag"
interpretation.
And here's something else
where I've added the things
in the heavy blue boxes.
They're the relationship
between the--
a node and the viewer, that
is to be more explicit.
The coordinate transformation
between the intrinsic frame
of reference of the crown
and the intrinsic frame
of reference of the viewer,
your eyeball is that Rwv.
And that's a different
kind of thing
altogether because as you
change viewpoint, that changes.
In fact, as you
change viewpoint,
all those things
in blue boxes all
change together in
a consistent way.
And there's a
simple relationship,
which is that if you take Rwv
then you multiply it by Rwx,
you get Rxv.
So you can easily propagate
viewpoint information
over a structural description.
And that's what I think
a mental image is.
Rather than a bunch
of pixels, it's
a structural description
with associated viewpoint
information.
That makes sense of a lot of
properties of mental images,
like if you want to do any
reasoning with things like Rwx,
you form a mental image,
that is you fill in
or you choose a viewpoint.
And I want to do one more demo
to convince you you always
choose a viewpoint when
you're solving mental imagery
problems.
So I'm going to give you another
very simple mental imagery
problem.
At the risk of
running over time.
Imagine that you're
at a particular point
and you travel a mile east, and
then you travel a mile north,
and then you travel
a mile east again.
What's your direction back
to your starting point?
This isn't a very hard problem.
It's sort of a bit South
and quite a lot west, right?
It's not exactly southwest,
but it's sort of southwest.
Now, when you did that
task, what you imagined
from your point of view
is you went a mile east,
and then you went a
mile north, and then
you went a mile east again.
I'll tell you what
you didn't imagine.
You didn't imagine that
you went a mile east,
and you went a mile
north, and then
you went a mile east again.
You could have solved
the problem perfectly
well with north not being up.
But you had north up.
You also didn't imagine this.
You got a mile east, and
then a mile north, and then
a mile east again.
And you didn't imagine this.
You go a mile east, and
then a mile north and so on.
You imagined it at
a particular scale
in a particular orientation
and in a particular position.
And you can answer questions
about roughly how big
it was and so on.
So that's evidence that
to solve these tasks that
involve using relationships
between things,
you form a mental image.
OK, enough on mental imagery.
So I'm now going to give you
a very brief introduction
to contrastive
learning, where this
is a complete
disconnect in the talk,
but they'll come
back together soon.
So in contrast to
self-supervised learning, what
we try and do is make two
different crops of an image
have the same representation.
There's a paper a long time
ago by Becker and Hinton
where we're doing this to
discover low-level coherence
in an image, like the
continuity of surfaces
or the depth of surfaces.
It's been improved
a lot since then.
And it's been used for doing
things like classification.
That is you take an image that
has one prominent object in it
and you say if I take a crop
of the image that contains sort
of any part of that
object, it should
have the same representation
as some other crop
of the image containing
a part of that object.
And this has been developed
a lot in the last few years.
I'm going to talk
about a model developed
a couple of years ago by my
group in Toronto called SimCLR.
But there's lots
of other models.
And since then,
things have improved.
So in SimCLR, you
take an image x.
You take two different crops.
And you also do color distortion
of the crops, different color
distortions of each crop.
And that's to prevent it
from using color histograms
to say they're the same.
So you mess with the color
so it can't use color
in a simple way.
And that gives you xi
tilde, and xj tilde.
You then put those through
the same neural network, f.
Then you get a representation h.
And then you take
the representation h,
and you put it through
another neural network,
which compresses it a bit.
And it goes to low
dimensionality.
That's an extra complexity
I'm not going to explain,
but it makes it
work a bit better.
You can do it
without doing that.
And you get two
embeddings, zi and zj.
And your aim is to
maximize the agreement
between those vectors.
And so you start off doing that.
And you say, OK, let's start
off with random neural networks,
random weights in
the neural networks.
And let's take two patches.
And let's put them through
these transformations.
And let's try and make
zi be the same as zj.
So let's back propagate
the squared difference
between components of
i and components of j.
And hey, presto,
what you discover
is when everything
collapses, for every image,
it will always produce
the same zi and zj.
And then you realize,
well, that's not
what I meant by agreement.
I mean, they should
be the same when
you get two crops of the
same image and different
when you get two crops
with different images.
Otherwise, there's not
really agreement, right?
So you have to have
negative examples.
You have to show it crops
from different images
and say those
should be different.
If they're already
different, you
don't try and make them
a lot more different.
It's very easy to make
things very different,
but that's not what you want.
You just want to be sure
they're different enough
so crops from different
images aren't taken
to be from the same image.
So if they happen to be very
similar, you push them apart.
And that stops your
representations collapsing.
That's called
contrastive learning.
And it works very well.
So what you can do is
do unsupervised learning
by trying to maximize agreement
between the representations you
get from two image patches
from the same image.
And after you've
done that, you just
take your representation
of the image patch,
and you feed it to a linear
classifier, a bunch of weights
so that you multiply the
representation by a weight
matrix, put it through a
softmax and get close labels.
And then you train that
by gradient descent.
And what you discover is
that that's just about as
good as training on label data.
So now the only thing you
trained on labeled data
is that last linear classifier.
The previous slides were
trained on unlabeled data.
And you managed to train
your representations
without needing labels.
Now, there's a
problem with this.
It works very nicely, but
it's really confounding
objects and whole scenes.
So it makes sense to say
two different patches
from the same scene
should get the same vector
label at the scene level because
they're from the same scene.
But what if one of
the patches contains
bits of objects A and B
and another patch contain
bits of objects A and C?
You don't really want
those two patches
to have the same representation
at the object level.
So we have to distinguish
these different levels
of representation.
And for contrastive
learning, if you
don't use any kind of
gating or attention,
then what's happening
is you're really doing
learning at the scene level.
What we'd like is that
the representations you
get at the object level should
be the same if both patches are
patches of object A
but should be different
if one patch is for object A
and one patch is for object B.
And to do that, we're going
to need some form of attention
to decide whether they really
come from the same thing.
And so GLOM is
designed to do that.
It's trying to take
contrastive learning
and to introduce a
tension of the kind you
get in transformers in order
not to try and say things
are the same when they're not.
I should mention at this
point that most of you
will be familiar with BERT.
Then you can think
of the word fragments
that are fed into BERT.
There's like the image
patches I'm using here.
And in BERT, you have that
whole column of representations
of the same word fragment.
In BERT, what's happening
presumably as you go up
is you're getting semantically
richer representations.
But in BERT, there's no
attempt to get representations
of larger things
like whole phrases.
What I'm going to talk about
will be a way to modify BERT So
as you go up, you get bigger
and bigger islands of agreement.
So, for example, after
a couple of levels,
then things like
"New" and "York"
will have the different
fragments of "York."
And suppose its got two
different fragments will
have exactly the same
representation if it
was done in the GLOM-like way.
And then as you go
up another level,
the fragments of "New"
or new's probably
a theme in its own right
and the fragments of "York"
would all have exactly
the same representation.
They have this
island of agreement.
And that would be
a representation
of a compound thing.
And as you go up,
you're going to get
these islands of
agreement that represent
bigger and bigger things.
And that's going to be a
much more useful kind of BERT
because instead of taking
vectors that represent word
fragments and then sort
of munging them together
by taking the max
of each component,
for example, which is
just a crazy thing to do,
you would explicitly
as you're learning
form representations
of larger parts
in the part-whole hierarchy.
OK.
So what are we going after
in GLOM is a particular kind
of spatial coherence.
That's more complicated than
the spatial coherence caused
by the fact that
surfaces tend to be
at the same depth
and same orientation
in nearby patches of an image.
We're going after the
spacial coherence that
says that if you find
a mouth in an image
and you find a nose
in an image and then
the right spatial
relationship to make a face,
then that's a particular
kind of coherence.
And we want to go after
that unsupervised.
And we want to discover that
kind of coherence in images.
So before I go into
more details about GLOM,
I want a disclaimer.
For years, computer
vision treated vision
as you've got a static
image, a uniform resolution,
then you want to
say what's in it.
That's not how vision
works in the real world.
In the real world,
this is actually a loop
where you decide where to look.
If you're a person
or a robot, you
better do that intelligently.
And that gives you a
sample of the optic array.
It turns the optic array,
the incoming light,
into a retinal image.
And on your retina, you
have high resolution
in the middle and low
resolution around the edges.
And so you're focusing
on particular details.
And you never ever
process the whole image
a uniform resolution.
You're always focusing on
something and processing
where you're fixating at high
resolution and everything
else at much lower resolution,
particularly around the edges.
So I'm going to ignore
all the complexity of how
you decide where to look and all
the complexity of how you put
together the information you
get from different fixations
by saying, let's just talk
about the very first fixation
of a novel image.
So you look somewhere
and now what
happens on that first fixation?
We know that the same
hardware in the brain
is going to be reused
for the next fixation.
But let's just think
about the first fixation.
So finally here's a picture
of the architecture.
And this is the architecture
for a single location,
so like for a single
word fragment in BERT.
And it shows you what's
happening for multiple frames.
So GLOM is really
designed for video,
but I only talk about
applying it to static images.
Then you should think
of a static image
as a very boring video in
which the frames are all
the same as each other.
So I'm showing you
three adjacent levels
in the hierarchy.
And I'm showing you
what happens over time.
So if you look at
the middle level,
maybe that's the sort
of major part level.
And look at that box
that says "level L."
And that's at frame four, so
the right hand level L box.
And let's ask how the state
of that box-- the state
of that embedding is determined.
So inside the box, we're
going to get an embedding.
And the embedding is going to
be the representation of what's
going on at the major part
level for that little patch
of the image.
At level L the--
in this diagram,
all of these
embeddings will always
be devoted to the same
patch of the retinal image.
OK.
The level L embedding
on the right hand side.
You can see there's three
things determining it there.
There's the green arrow.
And for static images, the
green arrow is rather boring.
It's just saying you
should sort of be
similar to the previous
state of level L.
So it's just doing
temporal integration.
The blue arrow is
actually a neural net
with a couple of
hidden layers in it.
I'm just showing you
the embeddings here,
not all the layers
of the neural net.
We need a couple
of hidden layers
to do the coordinate
transforms that are required.
And the blue arrow
is basically taking
information of the level below
of the previous time step.
So level L minus
1 on frame 3 might
be representing that, I
think, I might be a nostril.
Well, if you think you
might be a nostril,
or you predicted
the next level up
is a nose, what's
more if you have
a coordinate frame
for the nostril,
you can predict the
coordinate frame for the nose.
Maybe not perfectly but
you have a pretty good idea
of the orientation
position scale of the nose.
So that bottom up
neural net is a net
that can take any kind
of part or level in mind.
So it can take a nostril,
but it could also
take a steering wheel
and predict the car
from the steering wheel
and predict what you've
got at the next level up.
The red arrow is a
top down neural net.
So the red arrow is predicting
the nose from the whole face.
And, again, it has a
couple of hidden layers
to do coordinate transforms.
Because if you know the
corner frame of the face
and you know the relationship
between a face and a nose,
and that's going to be
in the weights of that
top down neural net.
Then you can predict
that it's a nose
and what the pose
of the nose is.
And that's all going to be in
activities in that embedding
vector.
OK.
All of that is what's going
on in one column of hardware.
That's all about a specific
patch of the image.
So that's very, very like
what's going on for one word
fragmenting BERT.
You have all these
levels of representation.
It's a bit confusing exactly
what the relation of this
is to BERT.
And I'll give you the
reference to a long Arxiv
paper at the end that has
a whole section on how
this relates to BERT.
But it's confusing because
this has time steps.
And that makes it
all more complicated.
OK.
So those are three
things that determine
the level of
embedding, but there's
one fourth thing, which is
in black at the bottom there.
And that's the only way in which
different locations interact.
And that's a very simplified
form of a transformer.
If you take a
transformer as in BERT
and you say, let's make
the embeddings and the keys
and the queries and the values
all be the same as each other,
you just have this one vector.
So now all you're trying
to do is make the level L
embedding in one column
be the same as the level
L embedding in nearby columns,
but it's going to be gated
and then you're going to
try and make it be the same
if it's already quite similar.
So here's how the
attention works.
You take the level L embedding
in location x, that's Lx.
And you take the level L
embedding in a nearby location
y, that's Ly.
You take the scalar product.
You exponentiate
and you normalize.
In other words,
you do a softmax.
And that gives you the
weight to use in your desire
to make Lx be the same as Ly.
So the input produced by this--
from neighbors is an attention
weighted average of the level
L embeddings of nearby columns.
And that's an extra
input that you get.
It's trying to make you
agree with nearby things.
And that's what's going
to cause you to get
these islands of agreement.
So back to this
picture, I think--
yeah, this is what
we'd like to see.
And the reason we get those--
that big island of agreement
at the object level
is because we're trying
to get agreement there.
We're trying to learn
the coordinate transform
from the red arrows to the level
above and from the green arrows
to the level above such
that we get agreement.
OK.
Now, one thing we
need to worry about
is that the difficult
thing in perception it's
not so bad in language.
It's probably worse
than visual perception,
is there's a lot of ambiguity.
If I'm looking at
a line drawing,
for example, I see a circle.
Well, the circle could be
the right eye of a face,
or it could be the
left eye of a face,
front wheel of a car
or the back wheel of a car.
There's all sorts of things
that that circle could be.
And we'd like to
disambiguate the circle.
And there's a long line
of work using things
like Markov random fields.
Here, we need a variation on
a Markov random field, which
I call a "transformational
random field"
because the interaction
between, for example,
something that might be
an eye and something that
might be a mouth needs to be
gated by corner transforms.
Let's take a nose and
a mouth because that's
my standard thing.
If you take something that might
be a nose and you want to ask,
does anybody out there
support the idea of the nose?
Well, what you'd like to do
is send to everything nearby
a message saying, do
you have the right kind
of pose and right
kind of identity
to support the idea
that I am a nose?
And so you'd like, for
example, to send out
a message from the nose.
You'd send out a message to
all nearby locations saying,
does anybody have a
mouth with the pose
that I predict by taking the
pose of the nose multiplying
by the coordinate transformed
between the nose and the mouth?
And now, I can predict
the pose of the mouth.
Is there anybody out
there with that pose who
thinks there might be a mouth?
And I think you can see you're
going to have to send out
a lot of different messages.
For each kind of other thing
that might support you,
you're going to send
a different message.
So you're going to need a
multi-headed transformer.
And it's going to be doing
these coordinate transforms.
And you have to coordinate
transform the inverse transform
on the way back because
if the mouth supports you,
what it needs to
support is a nose,
not with the pose of the mouth
but with the appropriate pose.
So that's going to
get very complicated.
You're going to have n
squared interactions all
with coordinate transforms.
There's another way
of doing it and it's
much simpler that's
called a Hough transform.
At least, it's
much simpler if you
have a way of
representing ambiguity.
So instead of these
direct interactions
between parts like a nose and a
mouth, what you're going to do
is you're going to make each
of the parts predict the whole.
So the nose can
protect the face,
but it can predict
the pose of the face.
And the mouth can
also predict the face.
Now, these will be in
different columns of GLOM.
But in one column
of GLOM, you'll
have a nose predicting a face.
In a nearby column, you'll
have a mouth predicting a face.
And those two faces
should be the same
if this really is a face.
So when you do this
attention weighted
averaging with nearby
things, what you're doing
is you're getting
confirmation that the support
for the hypothesis you got.
I mean, suppose for one
column the hypothesis
is a face with this pose.
That gets supported
by nearby columns
that derive the very
same embedding from quite
different data.
One derived it from the
nose, and one derived it
from the mouth.
And this doesn't require
any dynamic routine
because the
embeddings are always
referring to what's going
on in the same small patch
of the image.
Within a column
there's no routing.
And between columns, there's
something a bit like routing,
but it's just the standard
transformer kind of attention.
You're just trying to agree
with things that are similar.
OK, so that's how GLOM
was meant to work.
And the big problem is--
that if I see a circle,
it might be a left eye,
or it might be a right eye.
It might be a front
wheel of the car
or it might be the
back wheel of a car.
Because my embedding
for a particular patch
at a particular level has to
be able to represent anything,
when I get an
ambiguous thing, I have
to deal with all these
possibilities of what whole
it might be part of.
So instead of trying
to resolve ambiguity
at the part level, what I can
do is jump to the next level up
and resolve the ambiguity
there just by seeing if things
are the same, which is an
easier way to resolve ambiguity.
But the cost of
that is I have to be
able to represent
all the ambiguity I
get at the next level up.
Now, it turns out
you can do that.
We've done a little toy
example where you can actually
preserve this ambiguity,
but it's difficult.
It's the kind of thing
neural nets are good at.
So if you think about the
embedding of the next level up,
you got a whole bunch of
neurons whose activities
are that embedding.
And you want to represent a
highly multimodal distribution,
like, it might be a car
with this pose or a car
with that pose or a face with
this pose or a face with that
pose.
All of these are
possible predictions
for finding a circle.
And so you have to
represent all that.
And the question is,
can neural nets do that?
But I think the way
they must be doing
it is each neuron
in the embedding
stands for an unnormalized
log probability
distribution over this huge
space of possible identities
and possible poses, the sort
of cross product of identities
and poses.
And so the neuron is this
rather vague log probability
distribution over that space.
And when you activate the
neuron, what it's saying
is add in that log
probability distribution
to what you've already got.
And so now if you have a
whole bunch of log probability
distributions and you
add them all together,
you can get a much more peaky
log probability distribution.
And when you exponentiate, you
get a probability distribution.
It gets very peaky
and so very vague
basis functions in this joint
space of pose and identity
and basis functions.
And the log probability
in that space
can be combined to
produce sharp conclusions.
So I think that's how neurons
are representing things.
Most people think
about neurons as--
they think about the thing
that they're representing
but obviously in perception you
have to deal with uncertainty.
And so neurons have to
be good at representing
multimodal distributions.
And this is the
only way I can think
of that's good at doing it.
That's a rather weak argument.
But it's the argument
that led Chomsky
to believe that language wasn't
learned because he couldn't
think of how it was learned.
My view is neurons must be using
this representation because I
can't think of any
other way of doing it.
OK, I just said all that
because I got ahead of myself
because I got excited.
Now, the reason you can get away
with this, the reason you have
these very vague distributions
in the unnormalized log
probability space is because
these neurons are all
dedicated to a small
patch of image,
and they're all
trying to represent
the thing that's happening
in that patch of image.
So you're only trying
to represent one thing.
You're not trying to represent
some set of possible objects.
If you're trying to represent
some set of possible objects,
you have a horrible
binding problem,
and you couldn't use these
very vague distributions.
But so long as you know
that, all of these neurons,
all of the active neurons
refer to the same thing.
Then you can do
the intersection.
You can add the log probability
distributions together
and intersect the sets
of things they represent.
OK.
I'm getting near the end.
How would you train
a system like this?
Well, obviously, you could
train it the way you train BERT.
You could do deep
end-to-end training.
And for GLOM, what
that will consist of
and the way we trained the toy
example is you take an image.
You leave out some
patches of the image.
You then let GLOM settle
down for about 10 iterations.
And it's trying to fill
in the lowest level
representation of what's in
the image, the lowest level
embeddings.
And it fills them in wrong.
And so you now back
propagate that error.
When you're back
propagating, it's
through time in this network.
So it will also back propagate
up and down through the levels.
So you're basically just
doing back propagation
through time of the error due to
filling in things incorrectly.
That's basically
how BERT is trained.
And you could train
GLOM the same way.
But I also want to include
an extra bit in the training
to encourage islands.
We want to encourage big
islands of identical vectors
at high levels.
And you can do that by
using constrastive learning.
So if you think how at
the next time step--
if you think how an
embedding is determined,
it's determined by combining
a whole bunch of different
factors--
what was going on
in the previous time
step at this level
of representation
in this location,
what was going on
at the the previous time
step in this location
but at the next level
down or the next level up,
and also what was going
on at the previous time
step at nearby locations
at the same level.
And the weighted average
of all those things
are called a
"consensus" embedding.
And that's what you use
for the next embedding.
And I think you can see that.
If we try to make the
bottom up neural net
or the top down
neural net, if we
try to make the predictions
agree with the consensus,
the consensus has
folded in information
from nearby locations that
already roughly agree because
of the attention weighting.
And so by trying to
make the top down
and bottom up neural networks
agree with the consensus,
you're trying to make
them agree with what's
going on in nearby
locations that are similar,
and so you'll be training
it to form islands.
This is more interesting
to neuroscientists
than to people of
your natural language,
so I'm going to ignore that.
You might think
it's wasteful to be
replicating all these
embeddings at the object level.
So the idea is at
the the object level
there would be a large
number of patches
that all have exactly the
same vector representation.
And that seemed like a waste.
But actually biology is
full of things like that.
All your cells have
exactly the same DNA.
And all the parts
of an organ have
pretty much the same vector
of protein expressions.
So there's lots of
replication that
goes on to keep things local.
And it's the same here.
And actually that
replication is very useful
when you're settling
on an interpretation.
Because before you
settle down, you
don't know which things
should be the same
as which other things.
So having separate
vectors in each location
to represent what's going
on there at the object level
gives you the flexibility to
gradually segment things as you
settle down in a sensible way.
It allows you to
hedge your bets.
And what you're doing is
not quite like clustering.
You're creating clusters
of identical vectors
rather than discovering
clusters in fixed data.
So clustering, you're given
the data, and it's fixed,
and you find the clusters.
Here, the embeddings at every
level they vary over time.
They're determined by the
top down and bottom up inputs
and by inputs coming
from nearby locations.
So what you're doing
is forming clusters
rather than discovering
them in fixed data.
And that's got a
somewhat different flavor
and can settle down faster.
And one other advantage
of this replication
is what you don't
want is to have
much more work in
your transformer
as you go to higher levels.
But you do need longer range
interactions at higher levels.
Presumably for
the lowest levels,
you want fairly
short-range interactions
in your transformer.
And they could be dense.
As you go to high levels,
you want much longer range
interactions so you
could make them sparse.
And people have done things
like that for BERT like systems.
Here, it's easy to make
them sparse because you're
expecting big islands.
So all you need to do is see
one patch of a big island
to know what the vector
representation of that island
is.
And so sparse
representations will
work much better if you have
these big islands of agreement
as you go up.
So the idea is you have
longer range and sparser
connections as you go up.
So the amount of computation
is the same at every level.
And just to summarize,
I showed how
to combine three important
advances of neural networks
in GLOM.
I didn't actually talk
about neural fields.
And that's important for
the top down network.
Maybe since I've got
two minutes to spare,
I'm going to go back and mention
neural fields very briefly.
Yeah, when I trained that
top down neural network--
and I have a problem.
And the problem is if you
look at those red arrows
and those green arrows,
they're quite different.
But if you look at the level
above the object level,
all those vectors are the same.
And, of course, in
an engineered system,
I want to replicate the
neural nets in every location.
So I use exactly the same top
down and bottom up neural nets
everywhere.
And so the question is,
how can the same neural net
be given a black arrow and
sometimes produce a red arrow
and sometimes produce a
green arrow, which have
quite different orientations?
How can it produce
a nose where there's
a nose and a mouth where there's
a mouth even though the face
vector is the same everywhere?
And the answer is the top down
neural network doesn't just
get the face vector.
It also gets the location
of the patch, which
is producing the power vector.
So the three patches
that should get
the red vector are
different from three--
have different locations
from the three patches
that should get
the green vector.
So if I use the
neural network and I
guess the location as input as
well, here's what it can do.
It can take the pose, that's
encoded in that black vector,
the pose of the face.
It can take the location in the
image for which it's predicting
the vector of the level below.
And the pose is relative
to the image too.
So knowing the
location in the image
and knowing the poses
of the whole face,
it can figure out which
bit of the face it
needs to predict
at that location.
And so in one location,
you can predict,
OK, there should be nose
there, and it gives you
the right vector.
In another location, it can
predict from where that image
patch is there should
be a nose there,
so it can give you
the green arrow.
So you can get the same
vector at the level
above to predict
different vectors
in different places of the
level below by giving it
the place that it's
predicting for.
And that's what's going
on in neural fields.
OK, now, this was quite
a complicated talk.
There's a long paper
about it on Arxiv
that goes into much more detail.
And you could view this talk
as just an encouragement
to read that paper.
And I'm done, exactly on time.
Thank you.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Thanks a lot.
Yeah.